Guide to the Elbert Peets Papers, 1883-1983, 1904-1974 (bulk)
Peets, Elbert Papers
- Series II. Writings
  - Published Writings
    - "City Planner Believes Pope did Job he was Employed to Do" The Washington Daily News - draft, article re the Jefferson Memorial, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - "Washington, Williamsburg, the Century of Progress, and Greendale" - Architectural Book Publishing Co. - correspondence, book, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - "The Original Plan of Washington" House and Garden - magazine, correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - "Site Planning for Livability" The American City, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "Post-War Use of Temporary Housing Sites" The American City, Nov. 1943 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "Four Guides for Building a New Home" The Journal of Housing, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "The Neighborhood Concept" The Journal of Housing, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - "Studies in Planning Texture" Architectural Record, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Review of Deane G. Carter and Keith H. Hinchcliff, Family Housing in The Journal of Housing, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - "The Genealogy of the Plan of Washington" Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Review of Frederick Gibberd, Town Design in Landscape Architecture, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - "The Golden Horses" - on Washington, D.C. Civic Art, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - "East Front Pilgrims" The Washington Post - clippings, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - "The 'President's Square'" The Washington Post, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - "Le Plan du Major L'Enfant" - magazine, correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - On the Art of Designing Cities, book of Peets' essays edited by Paul D. Spreiregen - correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - On the Art of Designing Cities - correspondence, Mar. - May 1967 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - On the Art of Designing Cities - correspondence, June 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - On the Art of Designing Cities - notes, lists, c. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - On the Art of Designing Cities - draft, c. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 81-85)
    - On the Art of Designing Cities - layouts, c. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 86-88)
    - On the Art of Designing Cities - photos, c. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Unpublished Writings
    - "Some Design Aspects of City Street Trees" - Harvard School of Landscape Architecture thesis, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - "The Four Gods - A Socio-psychological Burlesque in One Act" - script, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - "Description of the 'Form-built' process of laying bricks", 1921 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - "The Unknown Art" - correspondence, drafts, 1923-1934 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - "Edgar Allen Poe, Landscape Gardener" - correspondence, manuscript articles, notes, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Notes and correspondence for a proposed book on estate design, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - "Differentiating Features of Cities as Seen from the Air" - outline, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - "'Lawns and Planting' Specifications" - report for Balitmore Housing Authority, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - "The Orientation of Row Houses" - article, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Mithradates the King" - short story, annotated draft, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Mr. Business, Meet Miss Summer Cottage" - typescript draft article, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Ohio in Song and Story" - manuscript article (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "The Beauty of Nela Park" - typescript draft article, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Gridiron Cities and Towns" - typescript articles (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "The Location of Monumental Buildings" - typescript articles, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "London" - manuscript and typescript article (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Away from Architecture", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Wolfflin - Kuntsgeschichtliche Grundbegriffe" - typecript draft article (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - An article on Street Trees, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Preliminary Indoctrination for Officials Enforcing the Old Georgetown Law" - typescript draft article (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - A series of articles on architecture and city planning (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Fragments of manuscript writings, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series III. General Papers
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1912-1921 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence with Jacob L. Crane and others, 1924-1926 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1929 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with Lewis Mumford, Jacob L. Crane, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1933-1938 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1953 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence with Anne Clapp, others, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - General correspondence, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence with American Institute of Planners, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Undated correspondence, A-C (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Undated correspondence, D-G (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Undated correspondence, H-L (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Undated correspondence, M-R (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Undated correspondence, S-V (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Undated correspondence, W-Z (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Undated correspondence, no identification (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Non-Peets correspondence, 1940-1968 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Notes
    - Notes, notebooks, 1925-1935 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Notes, notebooks, 1943-1950 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Notes, notebook, 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Notes on city planning, housing, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Notes on art, architecture, landscaping (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Manuscripts
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts on Art, Architecture, and Planning - articles, speeches, excerpts, 1922-1964 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Pamphlets
    - Miscellaneous Pamphlets on Art, Architecture, and Planning, 1902-1932 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Miscellaneous Pamphlets on Art, Architecture, and Planning, 1943-1960 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Miscellaneous Pamphlets on Art, Architecture, and Planning, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous Pamphlets on Art, Architecture, and Planning (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Clippings
    - Miscellaneous Clippings on Art, Architecture, and Planning, 1935-1963 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Brochures
    - Brochures, 1920-1956 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Photos
    - Pennsylvania - civic architecture, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Mt. Vernon, Virginia, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Masachusetts, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Weitz estate, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Europe, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - People, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - People, 1932-1963, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Home and family, 1930-1940, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Personal photographs, negatives, 1936, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Miscellaneous photos, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Miscellaneous photos, negative (some foreign), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - "Youngstown and miscellaneous street scenes and travel views" - negatives and photos of Youngstown, Ohio (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Graphics
    - Estates - plans and perspectives (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Perspective drawings, 1916-1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Perspective drawings, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - General Plan, Dr. and Mrs. W. A. Haldy, original., Oct. 30, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Summer Home and Garden, Miss Shewbrooks, Bolton Meadow, Mass., original., Mar. 7, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Plan for ...the Moraine Syndicate Property, West of Lake Forest, May 12, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Study for Walk between Cedar and Central, 25th to 55th, City Plan Commission, Cleveland, Aug. 14, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Study for Walk between Scovill and Woodland, 30th to 55th, City Plan Commission, Cleveland, Aug. 15, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Study for a Recreation Center on Whisky Island, City Plan Commission, Cleveland, Sept. 22, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Plan for ...Park ...Kingsbury Creek, City Plan Commission, Cleveland, Oct. 4, 1933. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Study for Stadium Grounds, City Plan Commission, Cleveland, Oct. 25, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Diagrammatic Sketch ...Stadium Grounds, City Plan Commission, Cleveland, Nov. 1, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Sketch Plan for expansion of Town Center, Feb. 1938 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Study for Emergency Housing, Aug. 20, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Study for ...development of ...Avalon Park, Chicago, Prudential Insurance Company of America, Newark, N.J., Loebl, Schlossman & Bennett, Architects, Sept. 10, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - M Street, original, Nov. 2, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Student work at Harvard, sketches made at the British Museum, 1921, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Plans and elevations, some done in Italy and France, some for The American Vitruvius (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Sketches, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Sketchbooks, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Palmanova - linoleum prints, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Peterborough Cathedral - linoleum prints, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - St. Paul's Cathedral - linoleum prints, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Martini - city plan - linoleum prints, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Majapahit, Java - city plan - linoleum prints, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Linoleum prints - blocks, 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous non-Peets graphic items - drawings, prints, plans, postcards, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Family and Biographical Material
    - Family and Biographical Material (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Family and Biographical Material - Edward O. Peets, Rumah Peets, Jan Van Bergen Collier - chart, correspondence, notebook, pamphlets, certificate, clippings, 1883-1952 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Miscellaneous Papers - poems, invoices, certificates, list, 1920-1964, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Printed material on Kohler Village and planned communities. (Box 6)
      Two offprints of articles co-authored by Arnold R. Alanen re some of Peets' work in Wisconsin: "Looking Backward at a New Deal Town: Greendale, Wisconsin, 1935-1980, by Joseph A. Eden and Arnold R. Alanen, and "Kohler, Wisconsin: Planning and Paternalism in a Model Industrial Village," by Arnold A. Alanen and Thomas J. Peltin. This is Greendale (paperback edition) by E. Peets. Note: Many of the photocopies in this box were made from our collection per K. Jacklin, June 1983.
    - Bibliography of Peets' writings on 4" x 6" notecards. (Box 6)
    - Folio of drawings and sketches
- Series IV. Plans, Prints, and Original Drawings in Map Drawer
  - School Projects
    - School Projects, 1914-1917. n.d. (Folder 1)
  - Town and City Plans
    - Washington Highlands, 1918 (Folder 2)
    - Wyomissing Park, 1922, 1924 (Folder 3)
    - Washington, D.C., City Plan, 1901-1960, n.d. (Folder 4)
    - Greendale, 1936-1949 (Folder 5)
    - Greendale, 1950-1960 (Folder 6)
    - Park Forest, 1946-1950 (Folder 7)
  - Private Residences and Estates
    - E. Richard Meinig, Wyomissing, Pa. - birdseye view from the east of the house and gardens, June 20, 1917 (Folder 8)
    - E. Richard Meinig, Wyomissing, Pa. - grading plan for the garden, Aug. 25, 1917 (Folder 8)
    - F. W. Norris - "Larchwood" - details of garden, Jan. 12, 1915 (Folder 8)
    - Keene Addington, Lake Forest, Ill. - preliminary plan, Sept. 15, 1915 (Folder 8)
    - Herman Vihlein [sic.], Pabst, White Fish Bay, Milwaukee, Wisc. - general plan for development of the estate, Sept. 16, 1917 (Folder 8)
    - Herman Vihlein [sic.], Pabst, White Fish Bay, Milwaukee, Wisc. - garden theater, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - Gustav A. Reuss, North Lake, Wisc. - plan for the development of the grounds of the gardener's cottage, Aug. 29, 1919 (Folder 8)
    - L. R. Smith, shore of Lake Michigan - sketch for the development, Scheme B, Dec. 21, 1919 (Folder 8)
    - L. R. Smith, shore of Lake Michigan - sketch for the development, Scheme F, Dec. 22, 1919 (Folder 8)
    - Myron T. MacLaren, Milwaukee, Wisc. - studies for the arrangement of steps to the east terrace, Oct. 1919 (Folder 8)
    - Myron T. MacLaren, Milwaukee, Wisc. - general plan for the estate, second copy annotated, Dec. 8, 1919 (Folder 8)
    - Myron T. MacLaren, Milwaukee, Wisc. - plan for tennis court, Apr. 6, 1921 (Folder 8)
    - Myron T. MacLaren, Milwaukee, Wisc. - sketches for development, Scheme A, Birdseye, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - Myron T. MacLaren, Milwaukee, Wisc. - construction plan for mall and steps at east side of garden, June 1921 (Folder 8)
    - Myron T. MacLaren, Milwaukee, Wisc. - general plan for the estate, July 30, 1921 (Folder 8)
    - Fred Pabst, Oconomowoe - revised plan for garden, June 13, 1921 (Folder 8)
    - H. Z. Logan, South Milwaukee, Wisc. - garden house, Nov. 2, 1921 (Folder 8)
    - George W. Rossetter, West of Lake Forest, Ill. - study for general plan, June 5, 1928 (Folder 8)
    - Private Residences and Estates, 1928 (Folder 9)
      A series of numbered drawings - the first five titled "Estate No. One" and "Estate No. Two" - without titles, but illustrating various landscape designs based on classical or baroque style. Some are annotated indicating that they may have been intended for publication.
    - Graham, St. Mary's Road, Libertyville, Ill. - first study, Jan. 25, 1930 (Folder 10)
    - Richter, Dick and Reuthmann - sales office at Washington Highlands [verso of above], Nov. 1917 (Folder 10)
    - Graham, "Five Pines," St. Mary's Road, Libertyville, Ill. - plan for vicinity of house (2 copies), Mar. 1, 1930 (Folder 10)
    - Graham, "Five Pines," St. Mary's Road, Libertyville, Ill. - construction details (2 copies), Mar. 2, 1930 (Folder 10)
    - Alfred MacArthur, 29 South La Salle Street, Chicago, Ill. - studies for development of lots in 40acre tract on St. Mary's Road, Lake Forest, Ill., May 1, 1928 (Folder 10)
    - A. M. Johnson and Alfred MacArthur, Lake Forest, Ill. - study for a community development on property west of Lake Forest, June 1, 1928 (Folder 10)
    - Alfred MacArthur, Lake Forest, Ill. - plan for vicinity of house (2 copies), Mar. 22, 1929 (Folder 10)
    - Alfred MacArthur, Lake Forest, Ill. - plan for vicinity of house, Mar. 29, 1929 (Folder 10)
    - Alfred MacArthur, Lake Forest, Ill. - working plans for south arbor, north arbor, milk house trellis and end of wall (2 copies), Mar. 31, 1929 (Folder 10)
    - Mrs. Paul V. Harper, St. Mary's and Old School Roads, Lake Forest, Libertyville, Ill. - cabinet work in dressing room, etc. (2 copies), May 1929 (Folder 10)
    - Miss Weitz, Zoar, Ohio - plan for retaining wall and pavement, Oct. 6, 1930 (Folder 11)
    - Miss Weitz, Zoar, Ohio - new east wing for ...log house (second copy with annotations), Oct. 6, 1930 (Folder 11)
    - Voevodsky, St. Mary's Road, Libertyville, Ill. - topographic map, Aug. 24, 1934 (Folder 11)
    - Voevodsky, St. Mary's Road, Libertyville, Ill. - general plan (2 copies), Aug. 31, 1934 (Folder 11)
    - Ben E. Cohen's Farm, Fairfield, Lake County, Ill. - plan for vicinity of the house, Mar. 30, 1935 (Folder 11)
    - Stevenson, St. Mary's Road, Libertyville, Lake County, Ill. - topographic map, Mar. 1935 (Folder 11)
    - Abbot, Fremont, Neb. - sketch (not Peets), n.d. (Folder 11)
    - W. O. Lindley, Lake Forest, Ill. - sketch plan of grounds (Folder 11)
  - Memorials, Parks, and Recreation Areas
    - Memorials, Parks, and Recreation Areas, 1932-1957 (Folder 12)
    - Memorials, Parks, and Recreation Areas, 1959-1960 (Folder 13)
    - Memorials, Parks, and Recreation Areas, 1961-1963 (Folder 14)
  - Other Projects
    - Other Projects, 1913-1930 (Folder 15)
    - Other Projects, 1931-1933 (Folder 16)
    - Other Projects, 1933-1956 (Folder 17)
    - Other Projects, 1956-1960 (Folder 18)
    - Other Projects, n.d. (Folder 19)
    - Other Projects, n.d. (Folder 20-23)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books - cataloged individually in the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections
The American Vitruvius: An Architect's Handbook of Civic Art, by W. Hegemann and E. Peets, 1922, Rare NA9030 H46 ++
The American Vitruvius: An Architect's Handbook of Civic Art, by W. Hegemann and E. Peets, republication by Princeton Architectural Press with new introductory essays. 1988, Rare NA9030 H46 1988 ++